The White Ship白船


I am Basil Elton, keeper of the North Point light that my father and grandfather kept before me. Far from the shore stands the grey lighthouse, above sunken slimy rocks that are seen when the tide is low, but unseen when the tide is high. Past that beacon for a century have swept the majestic barques of the seven seas. In the days of my grandfather there were many; in the days of my father not so many; and now there are so few that I sometimes feel strangely alone, as though I were the last man on our planet.

我是博西爾 埃爾頓，如同我父親和祖父經歷的歲月一樣，同樣是北角燈塔的守塔人，那是一座遠離海岸的暗灰色燈塔，光滑的岩石在退潮時露出海面，漲潮時沉入海潮中。 在過去一個世紀裡，燈塔的光芒引導航經七海的諸多雄偉船隻。 在那個光輝歲月裡，我祖父擔任守塔人時還能看到很多船隻經過， 輪到我父親的時候少了些，如今以經寥寥無幾。因此有時我會感到孤獨，彷彿地球上只留下我一人。

From far shores came those white-sailed argosies of old; from far Eastern shores where warm suns shine and sweet odours linger about strange gardens and gay temples. The old captains of the sea came often to my grandfather and told him of these things, which in turn he told to my father, and my father told to me in the long autumn evenings when the wind howled eerily from the East. And I have read more of these things, and of many things besides, in the books men gave me when I was young and filled with wonder.

來自遙遠海洋的古老白帆船啊; 航自遙遠的東方海岸，和煦的陽光和甜蜜的氣味流淌在奇特的花園和的海角的寺廟裡。 海上的老船長經常告訴我祖父的那些傳說，輾轉又告訴了我父親。當父親在漫漫秋夜告訴我那些遙遠故事時，東風正詭異地呼嚎著。 而我自己讀了更多這些傳說，讓我的兒時回憶充滿了奇幻。

But more wonderful than the lore of old men and the lore of books is the secret lore of ocean. Blue, green, grey, white, or black; smooth, ruffled, or mountainous; that ocean is not silent. All my days have I watched it and listened to it, and I know it well. At first it told to me only the plain little tales of calm beaches and near ports, but with the years it grew more friendly and spoke of other things; of things more strange and more distant in space and in time. Sometimes at twilight the grey vapours of the horizon have parted to grant me glimpses of the ways beyond; and sometimes at night the deep waters of the sea have grown clear and phosphorescent, to grant me glimpses of the ways beneath. And these glimpses have been as often of the ways that were and the ways that might be, as of the ways that are; for ocean is more ancient than the mountains, and freighted with the memories and the dreams of Time.

但是，比老人的傳述和書本更為奇妙的是海洋蘊含的秘密。 藍色，綠色，灰色，白色或黑色浪濤; 平滑，皺褶或山巒綿延起伏的海岸;其實海洋並不沉默。 我所有的日子都在看著，聽著，而且我很清楚。 起初它告訴我只有平靜的海灘和附近的港口平原的小故事，但隨著歲月變得更承平，開始談到其他的事情; 在空間和時間上更陌生，更遙遠的事物。 有時在黃昏的時候，地平線上的灰色蒸汽分開了，讓我看到了超越的方式。 有時在深夜，深海的海水變得清澈明亮，讓我瞥見下面的道路。 而這些瞥見就像往常一樣，也是如此， 因為海洋比山脈更古老，隨著時光的回憶和夢想而運行。

Out of the South it was that the White Ship used to come when the moon was full and high in the heavens. Out of the South it would glide very smoothly and silently over the sea. And whether the sea was rough or calm, and whether the wind was friendly or adverse, it would always glide smoothly and silently, its sails distant and its long strange tiers of oars moving rhythmically. One night I espied upon the deck a man, bearded and robed, and he seemed to beckon me to embark for fair unknown shores. Many times afterward I saw him under the full moon, and ever did he beckon me.

從南方出發，當月亮充滿，天空高高的時候，這艘白船曾經來過。 在南方之外，它會非常順利地，無聲地滑過海面。 無論海面風平浪靜，風況友善還是不利，總是平靜無聲地滑行，帆遠，船長奇怪的槳層有節奏地運動著。 有一天晚上，我在甲板上看到一個穿著鬍子和長袍的男子，他似乎招手邀我走向未知的海岸。我經常在滿月的時候目睹他多次向我招手。

Very brightly did the moon shine on the night I answered the call, and I walked out over the waters to the White Ship on a bridge of moonbeams. The man who had beckoned now spoke a welcome to me in a soft language I seemed to know well, and the hours were filled with soft songs of the oarsmen as we glided away into a mysterious South, golden with the glow of that full, mellow moon.

月亮照得很亮，就在我回應招喚的那天晚上，我走到水面上，在一座月光照耀下的白色的船上。 招手的男人現在用一種我似乎熟悉的柔和的語言來歡迎我，當時我們彷彿正在溶入一個充滿神秘南方金色光芒，充滿柔和的歌聲和月光的境地。

And when the day dawned, rosy and effulgent, I beheld the green shore of far lands, bright and beautiful, and to me unknown. Up from the sea rose lordly terraces of verdure, tree-studded, and shewing here and there the gleaming white roofs and colonnades of strange temples. As we drew nearer the green shore the bearded man told me of that land, the Land of Zar, where dwell all the dreams and thoughts of beauty that come to men once and then are forgotten. And when I looked upon the terraces again I saw that what he said was true, for among the sights before me were many things I had once seen through the mists beyond the horizon and in the phosphorescent depths of ocean. There too were forms and fantasies more splendid than any I had ever known; the visions of young poets who died in want before the world could learn of what they had seen and dreamed. But we did not set foot upon the sloping meadows of Zar, for it is told that he who treads them may nevermore return to his native shore.

天色漸亮，光輝燦爛的時候，我看到遠處的綠色的海岸，光明而美麗，對我來說也是未知的。從海上升起一片翠綠的樹林，樹木茂盛，在這里和那裡展開著閃閃發光的白色屋頂和奇特的廟宇柱廊。當我們靠近綠色的海岸時，那個長著鬍子的人告訴了我那個地方 - 扎爾的土地，那裡曾經留下了所有人們夢寐以求的美好夢想。當我再次看到梯田時，我看到他所說的是真實的，因為在我之前的景觀中，有很多我曾經透過超出地平線和海洋磷光深處的迷霧看到的。形式和幻想也比我所知道的更加輝煌。那些在世界面前死去的青年詩人的異象可以學習他們所看到和夢想的東西。但是我們並沒有踏上紮爾傾斜的草原，因為有人告訴說，踩到他們的人可能永遠也不會回到他的本土。

As the White Ship sailed silently away from the templed terraces of Zar, we beheld on the distant horizon ahead the spires of a mighty city; and the bearded man said to me: “This is Thalarion, the City of a Thousand Wonders, wherein reside all those mysteries that man has striven in vain to fathom.” And I looked again, at closer range, and saw that the city was greater than any city I had known or dreamed of before. Into the sky the spires of its temples reached, so that no man might behold their peaks; and far back beyond the horizon stretched the grim, grey walls, over which one might spy only a few roofs, weird and ominous, yet adorned with rich friezes and alluring sculptures. I yearned mightily to enter this fascinating yet repellent city, and besought the bearded man to land me at the stone pier by the huge carven gate Akariel; but he gently denied my wish, saying: “Into Thalarion, the City of a Thousand Wonders, many have passed but none returned. Therein walk only daemons and mad things that are no longer men, and the streets are white with the unburied bones of those who have looked upon the eidolon Lathi, that reigns over the city.” So the White Ship sailed on past the walls of Thalarion, and followed for many days a southward-flying bird, whose glossy plumage matched the sky out of which it had appeared.

當白船靜靜地遠離扎爾的梯田時，我們看見遠處地平線上的一座強大城市的尖塔。那個有鬍子的人對我說：“這是一個千奇百怪的城市，那里居住著所有那些徒勞無功地揣測的奧秘。”我又仔細地看了一眼，發現這個城市是比我以前所知道或夢想過的任何一個城市都要大。天空的尖頂到了天空，所以沒有人能看到他們的山峰。遠遠超出了地平線，把灰色的灰色牆壁拉得很緊，在那裡只能窺探到幾個屋頂，奇怪而又不祥，卻裝飾著豐富的頭飾和誘人的雕塑。我渴望進入這個迷人又令人心動的城市，並且懇求那個有鬍子的人把我放在巨大的卡門大門Akariel的石頭碼頭上。但是他輕輕地否定了我的願望，說：“進入千禧之城的Thalarion，許多人已經過去了，但沒有一個回來。在那裡，只有那些不再是男人的守護神和瘋狂的東西才行走，而街道是白色的，還有那些看著城市的死亡之神萊昂的未被埋葬的骨頭。“於是，這艘白色的船駛過了Thalarion ，隨之而來的是一隻南飛的鳥，它的光滑羽毛與它出現的天空相匹配。

Then came we to a pleasant coast gay with blossoms of every hue, where as far inland as we could see basked lovely groves and radiant arbours beneath a meridian sun. From bowers beyond our view came bursts of song and snatches of lyric harmony, interspersed with faint laughter so delicious that I urged the rowers onward in my eagerness to reach the scene. And the bearded man spoke no word, but watched me as we approached the lily-lined shore. Suddenly a wind blowing from over the flowery meadows and leafy woods brought a scent at which I trembled. The wind grew stronger, and the air was filled with the lethal, charnel odour of plague-stricken towns and uncovered cemeteries. And as we sailed madly away from that damnable coast the bearded man spoke at last, saying: “This is Xura, the Land of Pleasures Unattained.”

然後，我們來到一個怡人的海岸邊緣，每一個色彩的花朵，在內地，我們可以看到曬曬太陽下的可愛的小樹林和光芒四射的arbours。 從超乎我們的視野來的喧囂，湧現出一陣陣抒情和諧的歌聲，穿插著如此可口的微笑，我迫切希望劃手們繼續前進，渴望到達現場。 那個有鬍子的男人卻沒有說話，只是在我們走近百合花岸邊的時候看著我。 突然間，草木茂密的樹林裡吹來一陣風，帶來一股顫抖的氣息。 風越來越強大，空氣中瀰漫著災難性城鎮的致命的臭氣，暴露了公墓。 當我們瘋狂地從那個可怕的海岸航行時，那個鬍鬚的男人終於說道：“這就是沒有得到樂趣的舒拉之地。

So once more the White Ship followed the bird of heaven, over warm blessed seas fanned by caressing, aromatic breezes. Day after day and night after night did we sail, and when the moon was full we would listen to soft songs of the oarsmen, sweet as on that distant night when we sailed away from my far native land. And it was by moonlight that we anchored at last in the harbour of Sona-Nyl, which is guarded by twin headlands of crystal that rise from the sea and meet in a resplendent arch. This is the Land of Fancy, and we walked to the verdant shore upon a golden bridge of moonbeams.

因此，白船又一次追隨著天上的鳥，在溫暖的祝福海上，被愛撫的芳香的微風吹散。 我們日復一日地夜夜航行，當月亮滿了的時候，我們會聽到槳手的柔和的歌聲，就像在遙遠的夜晚，當我們遠離本土的土地時那樣甜美。 而在月光下，我們終於停泊在索納尼港口，那裡是由雙子座的水晶守衛，從海上升起，在一座輝煌的拱門相會。 這是幻想的土地，我們走到月光的金色橋樑上的青翠的海岸。

In the Land of Sona-Nyl there is neither time nor space, neither suffering nor death; and there I dwelt for many aeons. Green are the groves and pastures, bright and fragrant the flowers, blue and musical the streams, clear and cool the fountains, and stately and gorgeous the temples, castles, and cities of Sona-Nyl. Of that land there is no bound, for beyond each vista of beauty rises another more beautiful. Over the countryside and amidst the splendour of cities rove at will the happy folk, of whom all are gifted with unmarred grace and unalloyed happiness. For the aeons that I dwelt there I wandered blissfully through gardens where quaint pagodas peep from pleasing clumps of bushes, and where the white walks are bordered with delicate blossoms. I climbed gentle hills from whose summits I could see entrancing panoramas of loveliness, with steepled towns nestling in verdant valleys, and with the golden domes of gigantic cities glittering on the infinitely distant horizon. And I viewed by moonlight the sparkling sea, the crystal headlands, and the placid harbour wherein lay anchored the White Ship.

在索納尼的土地上，既沒有時間也沒有空間，既沒有受苦也沒有死亡。在那裡我住了很多年。綠色的草地和牧場，鮮豔的花朵，藍色的音樂和溪流，清澈的噴泉，以及莊嚴而華麗的Sona-Nyl寺廟，城堡和城市。在那片土地上，沒有任何的束縛，因為每一個美麗的景像都越來越美麗。在農村，在城市的輝煌中，隨和的人們都是那些慷慨大方，享受不到幸福的快樂人。對於我住在那裡的那些年代，我愜意地走過花園，那里古色古香的寶塔從賞心悅目的灌木叢中窺視，白色的走道與嬌嫩的花朵交相輝映。我爬上了山峰，從那裡可以看到迷人的全景，尖頂的城鎮偎依在青翠的山谷中，還有在無限遙遠的地平線上閃閃發光的巨大城市的金色圓頂。我在月光下看到波光粼粼的大海，水晶之岬，以及躺在白色船邊的平靜的海港。

It was against the full moon one night in the immemorial year of Tharp that I saw outlined the beckoning form of the celestial bird, and felt the first stirrings of unrest. Then I spoke with the bearded man, and told him of my new yearnings to depart for remote Cathuria, which no man hath seen, but which all believe to lie beyond the basalt pillars of the West. It is the Land of Hope, and in it shine the perfect ideals of all that we know elsewhere; or at least so men relate. But the bearded man said to me: “Beware of those perilous seas wherein men say Cathuria lies. In Sona-Nyl there is no pain nor death, but who can tell what lies beyond the basalt pillars of the West?” Natheless at the next full moon I boarded the White Ship, and with the reluctant bearded man left the happy harbour for untravelled seas.

在薩普遠征的一個晚上，我看到了一個晚上的滿月，它勾畫出了這隻鳥的召喚形式，並感受到了動蕩的第一個動搖。 然後，我和那個有鬍子的男人說話，告訴他我要去遠處的無人看見的Cathuria，但他們都相信超越了西方的玄武岩支柱。 這是希望的土地，在它裡面照耀著我們在其他地方所了解的一切完美的理想。 或者至少有這樣的人涉及。 但那個有鬍子的人對我說：“小心那些人說的Cathuria謊言的那些危險的海洋。 Sona-Nyl沒有痛苦也沒有死亡，但誰能說出西方玄武岩支柱之外的東西呢？“然而，在下一個滿月之後，我登上了白船，不情願的有鬍子的人離開了這個幸福的港口， 海域。

And the bird of heaven flew before, and led us toward the basalt pillars of the West, but this time the oarsmen sang no soft songs under the full moon. In my mind I would often picture the unknown Land of Cathuria with its splendid groves and palaces, and would wonder what new delights there awaited me. “Cathuria,” I would say to myself, “is the abode of gods and the land of unnumbered cities of gold. Its forests are of aloe and sandalwood, even as the fragrant groves of Camorin, and among the trees flutter gay birds sweet with song. On the green and flowery mountains of Cathuria stand temples of pink marble, rich with carven and painted glories, and having in their courtyards cool fountains of silver, where purl with ravishing music the scented waters that come from the grotto-born river Narg. And the cities of Cathuria are cinctured with golden walls, and their pavements also are of gold. In the gardens of these cities are strange orchids, and perfumed lakes whose beds are of coral and amber. At night the streets and the gardens are lit with gay lanthorns fashioned from the three-coloured shell of the tortoise, and here resound the soft notes of the singer and the lutanist. And the houses of the cities of Cathuria are all palaces, each built over a fragrant canal bearing the waters of the sacred Narg. Of marble and porphyry are the houses, and roofed with glittering gold that reflects the rays of the sun and enhances the splendour of the cities as blissful gods view them from the distant peaks. Fairest of all is the palace of the great monarch Dorieb, whom some say to be a demigod and others a god. High is the palace of Dorieb, and many are the turrets of marble upon its walls. In its wide halls many multitudes assemble, and here hang the trophies of the ages. And the roof is of pure gold, set upon tall pillars of ruby and azure, and having such carven figures of gods and heroes that he who looks up to those heights seems to gaze upon the living Olympus. And the floor of the palace is of glass, under which flow the cunningly lighted waters of the Narg, gay with gaudy fish not known beyond the bounds of lovely Cathuria.”

天上的飛鳥飛到了前方，把我們引向了西方的玄武柱，但是這次槳手在滿月之下沒有唱出那麼柔和的歌。在我看來，我經常會想像一下這個未知的Cathuria土地，那裡有輝煌的樹林和宮殿，想知道那裡有什麼新鮮的美食。 “我想對自己說，”Cathuria是神的居所，是無數的黃金之城。它的森林是蘆薈和檀香木，就像Camorin的芳香的樹林，在樹木中飄蕩著同情的鳥兒，甜美的歌聲。在卡杜里亞（Cathuria）的綠色山巒上，粉紅色的大理石雕刻著豐富的雕像和彩繪，在庭院裡放著銀色的噴泉，裡面放著一些銀色的噴泉。卡杜里亞的城市是金色的城牆，路面也是金色的。在這些城市的花園裡有奇怪的蘭花和充滿珊瑚和琥珀色的香水湖。晚上，街頭和花園裡都是用烏龜三色貝殼製成的同性戀照片，在這裡迴響著歌手和lutanist的柔和音符。卡杜里亞城市的房屋都是宮殿，每座宮殿都建在一座帶有神聖納爾格水域的芬芳運河上。大理石和斑岩是房屋，屋頂閃閃發光的黃金，反射太陽的光芒，增強城市的輝煌，幸福的神靈從遠處的山峰觀看。最美麗的是最偉大的君主多里耶（Dorieb）的宮殿，有人說這是一個半神人，還有一些人是神。多里耶布的宮殿是高的，牆上有大量的大理石塔樓。在寬敞的大廳裡，許多人聚集在一起，在這裡懸掛著時代的獎杯。屋頂是純金，鑲嵌在高高的紅寶石和天藍色的柱子上，有著諸如神和英雄的雕像，看上去高高的人似乎凝視著活著的奧林巴斯。宮殿的地板是玻璃的，在那裡，納爾格狡猾的水面上流淌著鮮豔的魚，在可愛的卡特里亞（Cathuria）的邊界以外，還沒有人知道。

Thus would I speak to myself of Cathuria, but ever would the bearded man warn me to turn back to the happy shores of Sona-Nyl; for Sona-Nyl is known of men, while none hath ever beheld Cathuria.

因此，我會對Cathuria自己說話，但是那個有鬍子的人會告訴我要回到Sona-Nyl的快樂海岸。 因為Sona-Nyl是人所共知的，而沒有一個人曾經見過Cathuria。

And on the thirty-first day that we followed the bird, we beheld the basalt pillars of the West. Shrouded in mist they were, so that no man might peer beyond them or see their summits—which indeed some say reach even to the heavens. And the bearded man again implored me to turn back, but I heeded him not; for from the mists beyond the basalt pillars I fancied there came the notes of singer and lutanist; sweeter than the sweetest songs of Sona-Nyl, and sounding mine own praises; the praises of me, who had voyaged far under the full moon and dwelt in the Land of Fancy.

在我們追隨鳥的第三十一天，我們看到了西方的玄武岩支柱。 他們被霧籠罩著，所以沒有人能夠超越他們或者看到他們的頂峰 - 有些人甚至說到達天堂。 那個有鬍子的人再次懇求我回頭，但我不聽他的話。 因為我迷上了玄武岩柱之外的迷霧，那裡出現了歌手和lutanist的音符。 比索尼最甜美的歌曲還要甜美，聽起來也是我自己的讚美; 那個遠在滿月下航行，居住在花梢之地的我的讚美。

So to the sound of melody the White Ship sailed into the mist betwixt the basalt pillars of the West. And when the music ceased and the mist lifted, we beheld not the Land of Cathuria, but a swift-rushing resistless sea, over which our helpless barque was borne toward some unknown goal. Soon to our ears came the distant thunder of falling waters, and to our eyes appeared on the far horizon ahead the titanic spray of a monstrous cataract, wherein the oceans of the world drop down to abysmal nothingness. Then did the bearded man say to me with tears on his cheek: “We have rejected the beautiful Land of Sona-Nyl, which we may never behold again. The gods are greater than men, and they have conquered.” And I closed my eyes before the crash that I knew would come, shutting out the sight of the celestial bird which flapped its mocking blue wings over the brink of the torrent.

因此，聽到旋律的聲音，白船駛入了西方玄武岩支柱之間的薄霧中。 當音樂停止，霧氣消散的時候，我們看到的不是Cathuria的土地，而是一個迅速奔騰的無法抗拒的海洋，我們的無助的海浪正在向著某個未知的目標邁進。 在我們的耳朵裡，傳來遙遠的水流雷聲，我們的眼睛出現在巨大的白內障的巨大的噴霧之前的遠方地平線上，世界上的海洋下降到絕對的虛無。 那個鬍鬚的人臉上流著淚說：“我們已經拒絕了我們可能永遠不會看到的美麗的索納尼之地。 上帝比人大，他們已經征服了。“在我知道會來的那場崩潰之前，我閉上了眼睛，把那隻在洶湧湍急的邊緣上搖動著藍色翅膀的天空鳥視而不見。

Out of that crash came darkness, and I heard the shrieking of men and of things which were not men. From the East tempestuous winds arose, and chilled me as I crouched on the slab of damp stone which had risen beneath my feet. Then as I heard another crash I opened my eyes and beheld myself upon the platform of that lighthouse from whence I had sailed so many aeons ago. In the darkness below there loomed the vast blurred outlines of a vessel breaking up on the cruel rocks, and as I glanced out over the waste I saw that the light had failed for the first time since my grandfather had assumed its care.

從那崩潰中走出黑暗，我聽到了人與人之間尖叫的聲音。 從東方來的暴風起來，當我蹲在濕在我腳下的潮濕的石板上時，使我寒冷。 然後，當我聽到另一次車禍時，我睜開眼睛，看到自己曾經航行過這麼多年的那座燈塔的平台。 在下面的黑暗中，籠罩在殘酷的岩石上的一艘船的模糊的輪廓，當我看到廢棄物時，我看到，自從我的祖父照顧以來，光線第一次消失了。

And in the later watches of the night, when I went within the tower, I saw on the wall a calendar which still remained as when I had left it at the hour I sailed away. With the dawn I descended the tower and looked for wreckage upon the rocks, but what I found was only this: a strange dead bird whose hue was as of the azure sky, and a single shattered spar, of a whiteness greater than that of the wave-tips or of the mountain snow.

在晚些時候的鐘錶裡，當我進入塔樓的時候，我在牆上看到了一個仍然保持的日曆，就像我在離開的時候離開它一樣。 天亮後，我下了塔，尋找岩石上的殘骸，但我發現的僅僅是：一隻奇特的死鳥，色彩如天藍，一顆破碎的晶石，白度大於 波浪提示或山雪。

And thereafter the ocean told me its secrets no more; and though many times since has the moon shone full and high in the heavens, the White Ship from the South came never again.

之後，海洋不再告訴我它的秘密; 自從月亮閃閃發光，很多時候，南方的白船再也沒有來過。


